Guide to the H. Robert Otness Collection of New York City Postcards and Photographs MC.245
New York University Archives
H. Robert Otness Collection of New York City Postcards and Photographs
circa 1930s
New York University Archives
Otness, H. Robert (Herman Robert), 1907-1995
MC.245
2 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 oversize flat-file folder
The H. Robert Otness Collection of New York City Postcards and Photographs contains postcards and a small number of photographs that document New York City's landmarks as they appeared in the 1930s. The collection was likely created by H. Robert Otness, who earned a Ph.D. from New York University in 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials. The accession number associated with this collection is 14.020.
Arrangement
The H. Robert Otness Collection of New York City Postcards and Photographs is arranged by format on the series level. Within each series, materials are arranged into folders alphabetically. Within the first series of postcards, landmarks that were especially well represented in the collection, such as the Chrysler Building and Washington Square Park, received their own dedicated folders. Other postcards are arranged in topical folders.
The second series contains photographs that were found in two small envelopes in the collection. The photographs were retained in their original order and placed within two folders corresponding to their respective envelopes.
The collection is arranged in three series:
I. Postcards
II. Personal Materials
III. Photographs
Biographical note
Herman Robert Otness was born in Moscow, Idaho, in 1907. He attended New York University between 1935 and 1939, graduating with a Ph.D. in clinical psychology from the School of Education in 1939. It was during these years at NYU that Otness may have collected the postcards and took the photographs that make up this collection.
After graduating from NYU, Otness worked as the chief clinical psychologist at The Training School in Vineland, New Jersey. He served in the U.S. Navy during World War II. In 1950 he accepted a position as associate professor of psychology at the University of Idaho, where he remained until his retirement in 1971. Otness died in Moscow, Idaho on April 21, 1995.
Sources: 1. Judith Nielsen, "Herman Robert Otness," University of Idaho Special Collections and Archives, March 1997. Accessed June 6, 2014. http://www.lib.uidaho.edu/special-collections/Manuscripts/mg379.htm. 2. New York University Commencement program, 1939.
Related Materials
For additional information about Otness, see the Herman Robert Otness Papers at the University of Idaho's Special Collections and Archives.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection contains postcards depicting New York City landmarks as they appeared in the 1930s. Landmarks that are particularly well documented in the collection include the city's churches, bridges, museums, hotels, and theaters, as well as the Chrysler Building, Empire State Building, Rockefeller Center, and the Washington Square Arch. There is a small number of photographs presumably taken by Otness during the same time period. Their subject matter is largely similar to that of the postcards in the collection: Washington Square Park is heavily featured, as is the RMS Queen Mary (which completed its first transatlantic voyage to New York in 1936), and the Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade. Materials also include ephemera collected by Otness while studying at NYU.
Postcards.; Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.
- Series I: Postcards, circa 1930s
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes postcards depicting New York City landmarks as they appeared in the 1930s. Landmarks that are particularly well documented in the collection include the city's churches, bridges, museums, hotels, and theaters, as well as the Chrysler Building, Empire State Building, Rockefeller Center, and the Washington Square Arch.
  - Aerial views, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bridges, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chinatown, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chrysler Building, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Churches, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - City views, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Colleges, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Coney Island, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Construction, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ellis Island, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Empire State Building, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Government buildings, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Grant's Tomb, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Greenwich Village, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harbor and waterfront views, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Herald Square, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hotels, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Madison Square Garden, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Medical Center, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Museums, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - New York Public Library, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New York University, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Parks, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - RMS Queen Mary, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Restaurants, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller Center, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Skyline images, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Skyscrapers (other), circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Staten Island, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Statue of Liberty, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stores, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Theaters, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Times Square, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Trains, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tunnels, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Wall Street, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Washington Square, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - World's Fair, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series II: Photographs, circa 1930s
  Series II includes a small number of photographs presumably taken by Otness during the same time period. Their subject matter is largely similar to that of the postcards in the collection: Washington Square Park is heavily featured, as is the RMS Queen Mary (which completed its first transatlantic voyage to New York in 1936), and the Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade.
  - Washington Square and the Queen Mary, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Parade and city scenes, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series III: Personal Materials, 1935-1939
  Series III includes ephemera collected by Otness while studying at NYU.
  - "The University Heights Campus of New York University" brochure, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Black Hawk Line bus schedule, 1935
  - Flyer for Earl Browder speech at School of Education, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New York Academy of Medicine library privileges, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Supervue of New York" poster by Samuel Freedman, 1937 (Flat-file 5, Drawer 17)
  - NYU Commencement programs, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The New School lecture ticket, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - NYU pennant, undated (Box 4)
  - Wooden NYU plaque, undated (Box 4)